The דף daf is ס"א, Samech Alef, sixty-one, although we start a
page before on ס' עמוד ב' Samech Amud Bet
by the two dots. So let's take a look, it's about ten
lines, twelve lines down in the wide
lines. אמר רב חנא בר רבה, Amar Rav Chana bar Rava, so
רב חנא בר רבה Rav Chana bar Rava said, השסועה. hashisuah. So
we are now talking about, we spoke about animals again, but still
within an אגדתא Aggadeta context. So it says
the
animal with split hooves, that's in the list of the תורה Torah
about the kosher and non-kosher animals, actually as was pointed out this
week's פרשה. parsha. So the actual פסוק pasuk is, let's see, זאת
הבהמה אשר תאכלו שור שה כשבים
ושה עזים, Zos hab'eimah asher tocheilu:
shor, seh k'vasim,
v'seh izim,
and then it says like this, אך את זה לא תאכלו ממעלי
הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה השסועה את הגמל ואת הארנבת. Ach es zeh lo
socheilu mima'alei hageirah umimafrisei haparsah hashisuah: es hagamal v'es ha'arneveth.
Don't eat this from animals with split hooves and then it lists
the ones that chew their cud. But the word is מפריסי הפרסה
השסועה, mafrisei haparsah hashisuah, those with split hooves, but then you know,
but השסועה, hashisuah, you could read the פסוק, pasuk, מפריסי הפרסה, mafrisei
haparsah, don't eat these with split hooves. Which is the first one
not to eat? השסועה, hashisuah, the שסועה. shisuah. So the גמרא Gemara
actually chooses to read the פסוק pasuk that way rather than as
an adjective but as the noun as a type of an animal
that is on the first of the list of things you cannot
eat. So what does he say? בריה בפני עצמה היא, Beryah bifnei
atzmah hi, this is a separate creature. יש לה שני גבים ושתי
שדראות, Yesh lah shnei gavim ushnei shidra'os,
it has two backs and two spinal cords, so I don't know
what it is. Okay, so it's in this list of animals that
we've never heard of before. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
וכי משה רבינו קניגי היה או בליסטרי היה V'chi Moshe Rabbeinu Kanigi
hayah o Balistri hayah?
Was משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu our master a trapper or a hunter?
So the word בליסטרי Balistri is like, you know, ballistras which means
like, you know, to catapult, you know, to throw things. So it
basically means like somebody that, you know, shoots weapons, and קניגי Kanigi
is apparently a word for a hunter. So how did he know
that there was this bizarre animal called the שסועה shisuah that he
should mention that in the list of non-kosher animals? Where did he
know about this? So מכאן תשובה לאומר אין תורה מן השמים. Mikan
teshuvah l'omer ein Torah min hashamayim. So here is a response to
those who say that Moshe made it up, that it's not from
God, because if that were true, how would he know to mention
this animal if he obviously could never have seen it before? Okay,
so that's the דרשה. drasha. Now,
אמר ליה רב חסדא לרב תחליפא בר אבימי, Amar lei Rav Chisda
l'Rav Tachlifa bar Avimi, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רב
תחליפא בר אבימי, Rav Tachlifa bar Avimi, זיל כתוב קניגי ובליסטרי באגדתך.
Zil kesov Kanigi uBalistri b'aggadetecha.
So he heard this דרשה drasha and said, 'Oh, that's like, go
write those two words, קניגי Kanigi and בליסטרי. Balistri. Those are interesting
words, I've never heard them before,' because obviously they're foreign words, right?
They're Greek words. So he says, 'Go when you, you know, like
when you record this אגדתא, Aggadeta, go like underscore these two words,
you know, maybe record what their meaning is or indicate to people
you're going to tell them over that they're foreign words because they're
not familiar with it.' But the use of these words definitely caught
his attention and he says, 'Go write those words down.'
Okay, ופרשה, uperashah, and make sure that you explain them, either when
you're giving over this דרשה, drasha, explain those words, not everybody knows
what it means, or maybe like write a marginal note on the
side so you'll remember what it is. Okay. Now, of course, it
could be that this is particularly a, you know,
a Babylonian אמורא Amora that is making this mention.
Presumably, when these originated in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, these types of
אגדתות, aggadetas, these Greek loanwords, they knew what they meant.
But if you're
telling this over, make sure you make a note to yourself what
these words mean. Okay, so now within that spirit we're going to
say a similar type of a point. חמשת סרני פלשתים, Chamesh sarnai
Plishtim, so in יהושע Yehoshua it lists the Philistine leaders, you know,
when they conquered them. Who are the Philistine leaders? העזתי והאשדודי והאשקלוני
והגתי והעקרוני והעוים. Ha'azzati v'ha'ashdodi v'ha'ashkeloni v'hagitti v'ha'ekroni v'ha'avvim.
So those five, and then it says the five Philistine leaders, and
it mentions six. So אמר חמשה וחשב שיתא, Amar chamishah v'chashiv shisa,
it says there're going to be five and it mentions six. So
how do you reconcile this? אמר רב יונתן, Amar Rav Yonasan, ארונקי
שלהן חמשה. Arunki shelahen chamishah. Their true like, you know, important leaders
are only five, the important ones are five. So the reason we're
mentioning this is this word ארונקי, Arunki, which is not a Hebrew
word or an Aramaic word. If you look at the side, some
have the גרסא girsa אדינדיקי Adindiki or something. Anyway, so אמר ליה
רב חסדא לרב תחליפא בר אבימי, Amar lei Rav Chisda l'Rav Tachlifa
bar Avimi, so again רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רב תחליפא
בר אבימי, Rav Tachlifa bar Avimi, כתוב ארונקי באגדתך. Kesov Arunki b'aggadetecha.
When you're in your like book of your אגדתות, aggadetas, write down
this word or write down this אגדתא Aggadeta but like note this
word ופרשה, uperashah, make sure you explain it. Like so again, this
is a strange loanword, don't know what it means, so make a
note of this with its explanation with what it means. Okay, and
now that we mentioned this דרשה, drasha, so his answer
was...
The sixth is really connected to the next פסוק pasuk as תוספות
Tosafot points out, the next פסוק pasuk right after listing these six
names says מתימן כל ארץ הכנעני Miteiman kol eretz hakna'ani
from the תימן Teiman the whole land of the כנעני. Kna'ani. So
what he says is you put the period before the word והעוים.
v'haivim. The five words are the five leaders of the פלשתים Pelishtim
and then it says והעוים v'haivim and the עוים, Ivim, they are
come from תימן, Teiman, which actually is better because if you'll notice
the five first five that it mentioned had a יוד yud at
the end. So the יוד yud at the end sort of suggested
this idea, you know, sort of implied like leaders of this tribe,
leader of this, you know, האשדודי, Haashdodi,
you know, whatever they were, you know, העזתי. Haazati.
When it got to העוים, Haivim, it didn't have the יוד. yud.
It didn't say העוימי Haivimi or something. So that really is connected
to the next פסוק, pasuk, they're not from the פלשתים, Pelishtim, they
are from תימן. Teiman. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught
similarly, עוים מתימן באו, Ivim miTeiman bau, they actually came from תימן.
Teiman. ולמה נקרא שמם עוים, Velama nikra shemam Ivim, why are they
called עוים? Ivim? שעוותו את מקומם She'ivtu et mekomam
because they either destroyed or they perverted their place. What does that
mean? That they, so רש״י Rashi says it means they left their
place because it was destroyed or they abandoned their place and they
destroyed it in their abandonment. Now why is all this significant? Because,
so let's, the גמרא Gemara continues, one minute, דבר אחר, davar acher,
עוים שאיוו לאלוהות הרבה. Ivim she'ivu lelohut harbe.
They desired many gods, meaning that the sense is that they left
their land, originally תימן Teiman is one of the grandchildren of עשו.
Esav. So they left their land of תימן Teiman and they came
to the land of the פלשתים, Pelishtim, so they either abandoned their
place or they had a desire, reading עוים Ivim with an אלף,
aleph, had a desire to worship other gods, so they were attracted
after the land of the פלשתים. Pelishtim. Okay, now, דבר אחר, davar
acher, עוים Ivim
or another explanation, שכל הרואם, shekol haro'am, anybody who sees them, אוחזתו
עווית ochazato avit seizes them great trembling. All right, so whatever given
explanation as to what עוים, Ivim, but they were not originally from
the פלשתים, Pelishtim, they were from תימן, Teiman, a grandchild of עשו,
Esav, and that's and therefore they have to be read with the
next פסוק pasuk and that's how it solves the problem of five
or six. Now, אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, and now we're
talking about these עוים Ivim are very fearsome people, דאית להו שיתסר
דרי שיני, d'is lehu shitsa darei shinei, they have 16 rows of
teeth, לכל חד וחד, lechol chad vechad, every one of them. Okay,
so now we're back in the theme about describing fabulous creatures. אמר
רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, הרבה מקראות שראוין
לישרף, harbe mikra'ot she're'uyin lisrof, there are many פסוקים pesukim that would
seem to a person, an unlearned person, that you could burn them,
meaning that they seem so trivial, you know, why are they even
written in the תורה? Torah? And nevertheless, when you understand them, you
realize that they are גופי תורה, gufei Torah, they are the very
body of the תורה, Torah, they are central to critical ideas in
the תורה. Torah. What are they? So let's, and here we're talking
about actually פסוקים pesukim in the תורה Torah itself, not just like
before where it was from יהושע. Yehoshua. והעוים היושבים בחצרים עד
עזה, V'haivim hayoshvim b'chatzerim ad Aza, so here mentions the עוים Ivim
again, right? That's the tie-in, the עוים, Ivim, the עוים Ivim who
dwelt in חצרים chatzerim to עזה, Aza,
which is a land in land of the פלשתים. Pelishtim. So מאי
נפקא לן מינה, mai nafk'a lan minah, why bother telling us? Right?
If you read the first פרשה parsha of דברים, Devarim, there are
all these little, you know, asides about, well, these people originally came
from here, and then they settled there. Like who the heck cares?
Why is that relevant? So מאי נפקא לן מינה, mai nafk'a lan
minah, so why do I care about this? Because מדאשתבע אבימלך לאברהם,
mide'ishtaba Avimelech l'Avraham, since אבימלך Avimelech swore to אברהם, Avraham, אם תשקור
לי ולניני ולנכדי, im tishkor li velini ulenachdi,
that because I am doing good to you, you have to do
good to me and you cannot, you know, you cannot sort of
betray, lie to, you know, act against myself, my children, my grandchildren
and so on. So אברהם Avraham had made a commitment to אבימלך
Avimelech as an oath.
So אמר קודשא בריך הוא, amar Kudsha Brich Hu, so God said,
so how are we going to do this if we have to
conquer that land and we have an oath not to take from
the פלשתים? Pelishtim? So God said,
ליתו כפתורים, leisu Kaftorim, let the
כפתורים Kaftorim come, ליפקו מעוים, lifku me'Ivim, let them depose, is that
the word? Depose. You only depose a king. Whatever. Anyway, kick out
the עוים Ivim that were originally living,
דהיינו פלשתים, dehainu Pelishtim, let them kick out the עוים Ivim that
were the פלשתים. Pelishtim. So this is like the first דרשה drasha
that עוים Ivim are פלשתים, Pelishtim, not בני עשו. bnei Esav. And
he says, let the כפתורים, Kaftorim, right, the פסוק pasuk says, כפתורים
היוצאים מכפתור השמידם וישבו תחתם. Kaftorim hayotzim miKaftor hishmidum vayeshvu tachtam.
The כפתורים Kaftorim that came from כפתור Kaftor deposed the עוים Ivim
and they settled in their place. So what is this about? Why
do we need this whole background? Because the עוים, Ivim, like the
first דרשה, drasha, are from the פלשתים. Pelishtim. If they had continued
living there, בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael would not be able to conquer
their land because אברהם Avraham had made an oath to the פלשתים.
Pelishtim. So God said, so therefore let the כפתורים Kaftorim come and
take this land of the עוים, Ivim, and then it will no
longer belong to the פלשתים, Pelishtim, and then בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
can conquer the land.
So וליתו ישראל, ve'leisu Yisrael, and let the Israel now come, וליפקו
מכפתורים, ve'lifku miKaftorim, and take the land away from the כפתורים Kaftorim
so it no longer is land of
the
פלשתים. Pelishtim.
I was gonna ask who who are the כפתורים Kaftorim identified as?
I don't know. Some some say that כפתור Kaftor is like Crete
or something like that.
That would make sense because historically archaeologists have concluded that the פלשתים
Plishtim were actually Greek.
Aha, so that's interesting. You mean the original פלשתים Plishtim at the
time of Abraham or the פלשתים Plishtim that were the more recent?
The more recent ones.
So that maybe is exactly you know the point about the כפתורים
Kaftorim that they took over from the פלשתים. Plishtim. Like it's sort
of like the people that were the Egyptians at the time of
the Romans were not the Egyptians at the time of Abraham, right?
Right, okay, right.
Okay, they were Greek too.
Right, exactly. Okay, all right. כי יוצא בדבר הזה אומר, Ki yoseh
badavar hazeh omer, in a similar way you say, כי חשבון עיר
סיחון מלך אמורי
היא, ki Cheshbon ir Sichon melech Emori hee, חשבון Cheshbon was the
city of סיחון, Sichon, and then it goes on and says והוא
נלחם במלך מואב הראשון, vehu nicham bemelech Moav harishon, and he had
fought against the first king of מואב. Moav. So why do I
need this history? Who cares about this history of nations? So מאי
נפקא מינה, mai nafka mina, who cares about this? דאמר ליה הקדוש
ברוך הוא לישראל, de-amar lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu le-Yisrael, cause God had
said to Israel, אל תצר את מואב, al tatzar et Moav, do
not oppress מואב, Moav, right? Because they are from לוט Lot and
you know and they're our relatives and whatever.
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, ליתי סיחון, leysei Sichon,
ליתי סיחון ליפוק מן מואב, leysei Sichon leyfuk mi-Moav, let סיחון Sichon
come and take the land away from מואב, Moav, all this land
on the other side of the Jordan, וליתי ישראל וליתי
מן סיחון, veleysei Yisrael veleysei mi-Sichon, and now let Israel come and
take the land from סיחון. Sichon. So there that's why the תורה
Torah gives us the backstory to explain you know why you are
able to settle in this land of the פלשתים Plishtim because it
was no longer belonged to the פלשתים. Plishtim. You know why you
were able to settle in this land of סיחון Sichon if it
was originally מואב Moav because סיחון Sichon came and conquered it from
מואב Moav so it was no longer belonging to מואב. Moav. והיינו
דאמר רב פפא, Vehaynu de'amar Rav Pappa, that's why רב פפא Rav
Pappa says, עמון ומואב טהרו בסיחון, Amon u-Moav tiharu be-Sichon, עמון Amon
and מואב Moav were purified by סיחון, Sichon, purified in the sense
means their land became permissible to the Jewish people because סיחון Sichon
had conquered. So when we took over the land of סיחון Sichon
and עוג, Og, it originally had belonged to עמון Amon and מואב,
Moav, but we were able to take it even though we're not
allowed to take from עמון Amon and מואב Moav because it no
longer belongs to them. The גמרא Gemara in גיטין Gittin by the
way learns from this a principle called כיבוש מלחמה, kibbush milchamah, a
principle called basically annexing territory based on war. That territories that kings
conquer on war, you might say, well it's just like stealing. No,
you know wars are almost like legally recognized and territory conquered in
war does belong to the conquerors. And therefore it no longer belonged
to עמון Amon and מואב Moav or no longer belonged to פלשתים
Plishtim and was no longer their land and therefore בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael were able to then take it. Okay, now since we're quoting
these פסוקים psukim and from דברים Devarim and to explain their significance
we're going to quote one other. צידונים יקראו לחרמון שריון. Tzidoniim yikra'u
le-Chermon Siryon. So it says the צידונים Tzidoniim would call חרמון Chermon
שריון Siryon and it says והא... veha...
something יקראו לו שניר yikra'u lo Senir and one other nation calls
it שניר. Senir. והאמורי
יקראו לו שניר,
veha-Emori yikra'u lo
Senir, fine. So both of these other nations have names for חרמון.
Chermon. Who cares what names they have for חרמון? Chermon? So the
גמרא Gemara says, תנא, Tana, שניר ושריון מהרי ארץ ישראל, Senir ve-Siryon
meharei Eretz Yisrael, so these are lands in Israel, right? Because the
חרמון Chermon is a mountain in Israel. מלמד שכל אחד ואחד מאומות
העולם הלך ובנה לו כרך גדול לעצמו, Melamed shekol echad ve-echad me-umot
ha-olam halach u-banah lo krach gadol le-atzmo, every one of the neighboring
nations built for themselves a nice big city on this
mountain, והעלו על שם ארץ ישראל, vehalo al shem Eretz Yisrael, excuse
me, right, I'm sorry,
not that חרמון Chermon itself, excuse me, not that חרמון Chermon itself
is from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but שריון Siryon and שניר Senir
are names of mountains in Israel. And חרמון Chermon was in the
land of these non-Jewish nations. So they built for themselves big cities
on the Mount חרמון, Chermon, but they gave the name to the
mountain, they used the names from the land of Israel. Like it's
like you know we live in New York, right, so this is
named after, right, or some people will say, oh you know this
is like this is the Alps of the United States or something,
so something is a very important thing you use that name to
a new location because you're borrowing from what to for you sort
of stands as like the model, right. So וילנה Vilna used to
be the Jerusalem of you know of Eastern Europe. So anyway, so
they're saying that they called חרמון Chermon שניר Senir and שריון Siryon
because they were naming it after mountains in Israel. Okay and that's
why the תורה Torah reports it.
מלמדך שאפילו הרי ארץ ישראל חביבין על אומות העולם, Melamedkha she-afilu harei
Eretz Yisrael chavivin al umot ha-olam, even the mountains of Israel are
dear to the nations of the world. כי יוצא בו, Ki yotsei
bo, in a similar way we say, ואת העם העביר אתו לערים,
ve-et ha-am he'evir oto le-arim, that יוסף Yosef after he you know
took all the wealth of the Egyptians... of the מצרים Mitzriyim when
he was during the years of famine and he said he purchased
them and then he purchased their person and not only that moved
them from city to city. Why did he do it? מאי נפקא
מינה? mai nafka mineh? Why is the תורה Torah telling us this
interesting fact about Egyptian history? Who cares? דלא ליקרו אחוה גלוותא. delo
likru achav galvusa. So he's teaching us that he did this for
the sake of the honor of his brothers, that they should not
say to them, "Oh, you people, you're foreigners. You came from the
land of כנען." Kena'an. No, you're also foreigners. You don't belong in
this land. This land is no longer yours. And he resettled them
to different places so that they themselves would not feel like, you
know, well, we belong here. You guys are, you know, you're the
foreigners. Yes.
I was wondering, this might have applicability today cause this, these passages
would imply that עזה Azah is, in fact, a part of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but Mount חרמון Chermon might not be. Why? Because
the former, the former we gave up control over, but the latter
we still control.
That's an interesting point. I mean, this fact that חרמון Chermon is
not part of Israel is the גמרא. Gemara. It's not clear, you
know, from the פסוקים. pesukim. Right. And, yeah, you have to look
at those maps based on the way the boundaries are drawn at
the end of במדבר, Bamidbar, but I think that's pretty clear that
חרמון Chermon is included, so I don't really know how to reconcile
that. Right. But, yeah, certainly the strip of land of עזה Azah
and whatever, certainly included in the boundaries drawn in במדבר. Bamidbar. All
right, that's the end of our אגדתא. Aggadata. Finally, we get back
now to the משנה, Mishnah, last line of ס' עמוד ב', Samech
Amud Beis, and here we really start with the official today's דף.
daf. I mean, with נ"ד, Nun Daled, so let's take a look.
סימני העוף לא נאמרו. simanei ha-of lo ne'emru. So the, so we
dealt with the indicators, the characteristics of kosher and non-kosher animals. Now
we deal with kosher, non-kosher birds. The משנה Mishnah says they're not
told in the תורה, Torah, but then it gives some type of
basic ways to identify: either non-kosher are דורס, dores, some type of
bird of prey; kosher birds have various characteristics about being able to
peel the gizzard etc. So let's take a look at what the
גמרא Gemara says. ולא, valo, is this really true that the סימנים
simanim were not given in the תורה? Torah? והתניא, ve-hatanya, we taught
in a ברייתא: braitah: נשר. nesher. So it says, you know, this
is what you shan't eat from the birds, and one of the
first mentioned is the נשר. nesher. By the way, the נשר nesher
we normally translate as eagle. It is most likely not the eagle
but most likely actually is the vulture based on other indicators, you
know, in how, in how the נשר nesher is described. But be
that as it may, the נשר. nesher. מה נשר מיוחד שאין לו
אצבע יתירה וזפק ואין קרקבנו נקלף ודורס. ma nesher meyuchad she-ein lo
etzba yeteirah ve-zefek ve-ein kurkevono niklaf ve-dores.
So here are the four characteristics that of what makes it of,
of the נשר. nesher. It does not have this אצבע יתירה, etzba
yeteirah, which we said was either the elongated middle finger or a
thumb-like finger. It does not, it does not have a זפק, zefek,
a crop. Its gizzard cannot be peeled, and it is a דורס,
dores, it is a bird of prey, ודורס ואוכל, ve-dores ve-ochel, and
it and sort of it, it, it claws, you know, it tears
and it eats. So what exactly the word דורס dores means, I
mentioned it when we did the משנה. Mishnah. I'll mention it again
in a minute, but let's just finish this thought. So טמא, tamei,
and that's not kosher. אף כל כיוצא בו טמא. af kol kayotzei
bo tamei. Anything like that also is טמא, tamei, anything that has
those four characteristics. תורין, Torin, now how about turtle doves, which are,
or pigeons, or
which are one of the קרבנות, korbanot, right? So what are those?
Or rock doves, or rock pigeons actually, we found out that when
we did that a while ago that a תור tor is actually
a pigeon, believe it or not. Anyway, שיש לה אצבע יתירה, she-yesh
lah etzba yeteirah, it has none of those four problems. It has
the opposite: שיש לה אצבע יתירה, she-yesh lah etzba yeteirah, it has
the extra finger, וזפק, ve-zefek, a crop, וקרקבנו נקלף, ve-kurkevono niklaf, and
a gizzard that can be peeled, ואין דורסין ואוכלין, ve-ein dorsin ve-ochlin,
they do not claw and eat. טהורין, tehorin, those are kosher. אף
כל כיוצא בהם טהורין. af kol kayotzei bahem tehorin. Anything that, similar,
anything with all four of these characteristics are kosher. Now, of course,
there's a huge gap, right? If it has, if it has four
negative characteristics, it's not good. If it has the opposite four, it
doesn't have any of those four bad ones, or let's say, you
know, describe it how you describe it as the four positive, it's
kosher. What about everything that's in the middle that has some of,
you know, a mix? So we're going to get to that in
a minute. But before we get to that, let's take a look
at how the גמרא Gemara answers. What do you mean it says
that there aren't the characteristics? Here we just have that the ברייתא
braitah says that we can identify the characteristics, and we can even
use these characteristics to determine what is a kosher and non-kosher bird.
So what do you mean that there aren't these characteristics? So the
answer seems pretty obvious. The גמרא Gemara says: אמר אביי לא נאמרו
פירושן מדברי תורה אלא מדברי סופרים. Amar Abaye lo ne'emru peirushan midivrei
Torah ela midivrei Sofrim. We're not saying that this is not a
biblical concept, we're just saying that we don't, it's not explicit in
the תורה. Torah. The rabbis had to come and identify what are
the significant characteristics. But in, but presumably, you can use these characteristics
even להלכה. le-halakhah. Now, that's going to get us into our interesting
conversation in a minute, which is can you determine kosher and non-kosher
birds based on these characteristics? Or do we say, in principle, it's
really not about characteristics at all? The תורה Torah lists, you know,
twenty, how much is it, twenty-four non-kosher
birds, and that's the end of the story. There are no, there
are no common denominators of kosher birds or of non-kosher birds. It's
either on the list or not on the list. Okay, so that
would be a strong statement of לא נאמרו פירושם, lo ne'emru peirusham,
you know, לא נאמרו מן התורה, lo ne'emru min ha-Torah, meaning not
Not only were they not explicit in the תורה Torah *Torah*, but
there's no point of characteristics in the תורה Torah, *Torah*. It's just
a question of being on the list. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, "Ah, but doesn't this ברייתא braita. *Baraita* indicate to us that
you can use certain characteristics to determine kosher or non-kosher?" It says,
"You're right. All we meant to say was it wasn't explicit in
the תורה Torah *Torah*, but you are allowed. It's not that it's
just a list. There are characteristics that you can use to determine
what is a kosher and non-kosher bird." Okay, and that's going to
be again very important if you don't know how to identify the
birds on the list. Can you still have ways of determining if
a particular bird is kosher or non-kosher? Okay, now before we get
on to discuss it, let me just say about again the דורס
*dores*, what דורס *dores* means. If you take a look at the
five lines down in the middle-sized line of the תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*,
דורס *dores*, פירוש הקונטרס שאוחז בציפורניו ומגביה מן הקרקע מה שאוכל *peirush
Hakuntres she'ocheiz bitfarnav umagbiha min hakarka ma she'ochel*. It grabs with its
claws and takes from the ground and puts it into its mouth.
So then he says, וקשיא לרבינו תם *vekashya l'Rabbeinu Tam*, this is
difficult according to רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*, דאפילו תרנגולות עושות כן *d'afilu
tarnegolos oseh kein*, chickens and hens do that. I remember we had
this exact debate yesterday or two days ago when I said that
that's what Rashi said דורס *dores* meant, but do chickens or hens
like peck at the ground, do they actually use their their hands
as claws to bring something to their mouth?
Anyway, תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says they do.
They, but they do
but they're not vegetarian.
Right, so apparently in this point of Rashi he didn't mention that
it had to be live, he just mentioned that it actually like
clawed, you know, picked it up with its hand.
And they like live worms and stuff.
Oh yeah, well that's interesting. So but okay anyway says ומפרש רבינו
תם *umefareish Rabbeinu Tam*, דורס ואוכל מחיים ואינו ממתין עד שתמות *dores
v'ochel mechayim v'eino mamtin ad
shetamos*. It eats something that is a live creature and eats it
while it's still alive. It doesn't first kill it and then eat
it, which of course is funny because there are certainly birds of
prey and whatever, you know, that are birds of like what are
they, vultures and whatnot that only eat carrion, although sometimes I think
vultures might attack live prey, I don't know.
But anyway, ducks are kosher and they eat live fish all the
time.
Really? Yeah.
Putting their head on the water and grab a fish and swallow
it.
Really? That's interesting. Okay, so unless again here it means live land
animals. So there's a whole question of exactly what you define as
דורס *dores* as a bird of prey. Again remember it's also the
word for דרוסה *derusah*, which was one of the טריפות *treifos*, which
meant like an animal that was clawed at by another animal. All
right, but now let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Now we're going to figure out now that we explained that line
in the משנה *Mishnah*, which means that it's not just about a
list, there are characteristics to determine kosher and non-kosher birds. Now we're
going to deal with the problem that we have a huge gap
between the list of kosher, between all four characteristics for non-kosher and
then the opposite four for kosher. What about everything in the middle?
So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
Okay, תני רבי חייא *tani Rabbi Chiya*, so רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiya*
taught, עוף הבא בסימן אחד טהור *of ba b'siman echad tahor*. If
an עוף *of* has just one kosher סימן siman *siman*. We let
mention four סימנים simanim, *simanim* of kosher birds. It's not a bird
of prey, it has an extra finger, it has a crop, and
it has a gizzard that can be peeled. So he says if
you have a bird that has just one of those, it's טהור
*tahor*. לפי שאין דומה לנשר *Lefi she'ein domeh l'nesher*. It's not similar
to the נשר nesher *nesher*, which again most probably means the vulture,
not the eagle. נשר nesher, דלית ליה כלל הוא דלא תיכול *nesher
d'leis lei klal hu d'lo teichul*. A נשר nesher *nesher* that has
no kosher סימנים simanim. *simanim* is cannot be eaten. היכא דאית ליה
חד תיכול *Heicha d'is lei chad teichul*. If it has just one
it is kosher. So he reads in this ברייתא *Baraita* that the
point is נשר nesher *nesher*, don't eat the נשר nesher *nesher*, don't
eat something with none of the kosher סימנים simanim *simanim*, anything with
just one of the kosher סימנים simanim *simanim* you can eat. So
then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, "One minute, but the ברייתא *Baraita*
goes on to the end to say that the kosher bird of
the תורין *torin*, of the pigeons, have all four kosher סימנים simanim
*simanim*. דלילף מתורין *Dileif miTorin*, why not learn off from the תורין
*torin*? מה תורין דאיכא כולהו ארבע Mah torin d'ika kulu arba, *Ma
Torin d'ika kullu arba*, they have all four kosher סימנים simanim *simanim*,
אף הכא נמי עד דאיכא כולהו ארבע Af hach'nami ad d'ika kulu
arba, *af hachanami ad d'ika kullu arba*, even here for until you
have all four kosher סימנים simanim *simanim*?" So it says, "No. אם
כן im ken, שאר עופות טמאים דכתב רחמנא למה לי *Im kein
shear ofos t'meiyim d'kasav rachmana lama li*? Then the תורה Torah *Torah*
would not have had to give you the whole list of non-kosher
birds." What does this mean? It means that we're going to see
in a minute that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands, you know normally,
normally I think here if you asked a lay person, what's the
story with this list of kosher birds, non-kosher birds, are there characteristics
or not? Your normal lay person would say, "Oh yes, yes, the
characteristics are bird of prey," right? That's what people know. Who knows
about crops and peeling gizzards or whatever? But people will say, "Oh
yes, the birds of prey are the non-kosher ones.
But you know, since we don't know exactly what's on the list
and not on the list, you know, if they know more that's
what they'll say, you need to have a specific tradition about what's
on the list." Okay, but presumably with an assumption that all the
non-kosher birds on the list share the same characteristic which makes them
non-kosher, but you need somehow to verify or to add to that
maybe specific knowledge about what is, you know, what is or is
not on the list. I mean at least that's sort of, you
know, the standard approach I know about my, you know, that sort
of people with a certain amount of informed information will say. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not actually saying that. The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
is saying two things. First of all it's saying that in principle...
And it's enough that it has any one כשר סימן kosher siman
and it would be כשר kosher כשר. kosher. So we mentioned four.
It's true one of them is that it is not a bird
of prey, but in theory the גמרא Gemara is saying and that's
what one of these long תוספות Tosafot is going out actually to
discuss, that if it were a bird of prey, but it had
an extra finger, or it had a crop, or it had a
gizzard that could be peeled, it could also be כשר. kosher. That
in theory, you could have a total bird of prey that's כשר.
kosher. Actually, תוספות Tosafot points out interestingly the reverse, that the גמרא
Gemara, is about to say that many of the non-כשר kosher birds
have one or two or three כשר kosher indicators, they just don't
have, and nevertheless they're still not כשר, kosher, and תוספות Tosafot actually
proves in this long discussion that actually even the majority of them,
like twenty or more of the twenty-four actually are not birds of
prey. Now that clearly is not true, I mean if you look
at any of the types of translations that are given to the
birds on the list, the vast majority if not all of them
actually are birds of prey, maybe it depends on how you define
what the word prey means, הדורס. ha-dores. But תוספות Tosafot actually claims
from the גמרא Gemara it emerges two things. Number one is a
bird could be not כשר kosher and not be a bird of
prey, and a bird could be כשר kosher and be a bird
of prey. So bird of prey is not like the be-all and
end-all indicator. So what is then the significance, how do you know
if it's כשר kosher and what's the significance of being on the
list? So what the גמרא Gemara is going to say or in
a minute, implicitly saying now is the following, is saying that if
it has none of the כשר סימנים, kosher simanim, then it is
definitely not כשר. kosher רש״י Rashi says it's a type of נשר
nesher, because according to רש״י Rashi you can't really add to the
twenty-four non-כשר kosher. birds. תוספות Tosafot says you don't have to say
it's a type of נשר, nesher it could be that the whole
point of the דרשה drasha is you have twenty-four names of non-כשר
kosher birds plus any bird that has none of the כשר סימנים.
kosher simanim, So having none of the כשר סימנים kosher simanim, puts
it on the list of non-כשר kosher birds. But if it has
some, a mix, some כשר סימנים kosher simanim some not, including maybe
a bird of prey, maybe not a bird of prey, if it's
somewhere in that mix, then it may be כשר kosher maybe it's
not כשר, kosher and the only way that we know that it's
not כשר kosher is which of those things that have some כשר
סימנים kosher simanim some not are not כשר kosher are ones that
are part of the list of the twenty-four. So that's the way
the גמרא Gemara is setting up this structure. Again, to be clear,
something that has all four כשר סימנים kosher simanim, like the pigeon,
turtledoves, whatever, those are totally כשר. kosher Anything that has none of
the כשר סימנים kosher simanim, like the נשר nesher, is non-כשר. kosher,
Okay, anything that's in the middle, that has some yes and some
no, including, by the way, some are birds of prey and some
are not birds of prey, because that's one of the four סימנים,
simanim, anything in the middle, some are כשר kosher and some are
not, some birds of prey are כשר, kosher some non-birds of prey
are not כשר, kosher anything that has some mix of the סימנים,
simanim, some are כשר kosher some are not, how you know which
is and which is not, if it's part of the twenty-four, it's
not, anything else is, okay? So that's the basic structure. So, with
all כשר סימנים kosher simanim, presumably you will know that it is
כשר, kosher. maybe. By the way, that remains the question. If something
has all four סימנים simanim do you also have to know what
the words of the list mean, what the birds of the list
mean, or can you say four סימנים simanim is definitely כשר kosher
regardless of what's on the list? That seems to be the case
because the גמרא Gemara is going to say that the only, all
the birds on the list in the תורה Torah have at least
one non-כשר kosher. סימן. siman. So presumably if it has four כשר
סימנים kosher simanim, you don't have to worry about the names on
the list, it's definitely כשר. kosher Has four non-כשר kosher, סימנים, simanim
I don't care if it's on the list, it's definitely not כשר.
kosher, Anything in the middle, it depends if it's on the list
or not, okay? So, with that one last point and then we'll
go back to the גמרא. Gemara
The
גמרא Gemara also assumes that of this list, which are twenty-four, twenty
of them have only one non-כשר kosher סימן. siman. Right, the נשר
nesher has all four negative or let's talk about positive סימנים, simanim
I think that would be less confusing. A נשר nesher has zero
positive סימנים, simanim, okay, the פרס peres and עזניה ozniyah have one
positive סימן, siman, the עורב oreiv has two positive סימנים, simanim, and
the, so that's a total of four now, and the other twenty
have three positive סימנים. simanim, So, and again תוספות Tosafot says by
the way that bird of prey is one of, a non-bird of
prey is included in the three positive סימנים. simanim, So according to
the גמרא, Gemara of the twenty-four non-כשר kosher birds, twenty of them
have three of the four כשר kosher, סימנים simanim. and תוספות Tosafot
goes so far to say and they're actually not birds of prey,
twenty out of twenty-four, which again is a little bizarre. Okay, so
anything that's in the middle of the list of a mix of
כשר kosher and not כשר, kosher I mean a mix of the
סימנים, simanim. you need to know its name, you need, if it's
on the list it's not כשר, kosher otherwise it is כשר. kosher.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So how do
you know to say, so what are we though including? We are
using, other than the birds named on the list, what we're saying
is other birds that have all, no כשר kosher סימן, siman, all
non-כשר kosher. סימנים, simanim those are also not
כשר kosher even if
Other than being on the list of explicitly mentioned by the תורה,
Torah what else is non-כשר? kosher So the way it’s set up
is what else is non-כשר kosher is even if it’s not on
the list, it has all four of the non-כשר kosher סימנים. simanim,
So the גמרא Gemara is saying is, well what makes you say
that? Maybe we should say that if it even has one of
the non-כשר kosher, traits, that should be enough to be non-כשר kosher,
even if it’s not on the list. Maybe it doesn’t need all
four non-כשר kosher. traits
to be non-כשר. kosher So the גמרא Gemara says if that were
true, so let’s read the response to that. The גמרא Gemara says
well let’s read the question again. ולילף מתורין, U'leif m'torin, why don’t
we learn out from the pigeons? מה תורין דאיכא כולהו ארבע, only
if something, maybe we should say only if it has all four
כשר kosher סימנים simanim, is it כשר. kosher אף הכא נמי עד
דאיכא כולהו ארבע, here as well, something needs all four כשר kosher?
סימנים simanim. and if it’s missing, and if it has just one
non-כשר kosher indicator, that makes it non-כשר, kosher even if it’s not
on the תורה's Torah list. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אם
כן שאר עופות טמאין דכתב רחמנא למה לי. im ken sh'ar ofot
t'meim d'kathav Rachmana lama li. If it were true, why did the
תורה Torah have to give me a list of twenty-four birds? Why
didn’t the תורה Torah just say any one non-כשר kosher indicator? The
fact that it gave me a list meant as a general rule,
some mix of כשר kosher and non-כשר kosher indicators, it would still
be כשר kosher. and unless you are specifically mentioned to be on
this list. But if one non-כשר kosher indicator was sufficient, you wouldn’t
need to list all these birds, of course they’d be non-כשר. kosher.
Okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says ונילף מנייהו? v'neirei m'naihu? מה התם תלתא לא אכלינן
אף כל תלתא לא ניכול, Mah hatam tlata lo achlinan af kol
tlata lo neichol, וכל שכן תרי וחד. v'chol shekein trei v'chad. So
why don’t we say like this? Why don’t we say, okay, but
the fact that as we just said, the majority of the birds
on the list, twenty of the birds on the list have three
כשר kosher indicators and they’re not כשר, kosher why don’t we say
that that becomes now our rule? That even if you have three
כשר kosher, indicators, meaning as since you have one non-כשר, kosher you’re
it’s still not
כשר, kosher meaning the גמרא's Gemara point what גמרא Gemara says well
if that's rule were true, you wouldn’t need to mention it. But
maybe you needed to mention it so we can infer the rule?
How do we know the rule of what the כשר kosher indicators
are? Right, but maybe it says because it gave us all of
these birds, we’ll infer, we’ll see, oh look, all these birds have
some different degrees of כשר, kosher non-כשר kosher indicators, but what we
do know is is that even if you have three כשר kosher.
indicators and just one non-כשר kosher because that’s the common denominator here.
They’re all the twenty-four birds on the list have at least one
non-כשר kosher, indicator, that that makes you non-כשר kosher and that then
becomes the rule. And you say, oh well if that were the
rule, why do you need to list the birds? You needed to
list the birds so that we can examine the evidence and to
figure out what are the non-כשר kosher, indicators. But now we know
that one non-כשר kosher, indicator suffices to make it non-כשר. kosher So
the גמרא Gemara says, so we would say מה התם תלתא, mah
hatam tlata, the same way by that there even three כשר kosher,
indicators it's still not good, so אם כן, im ken, so so
ולא אכלינן u'lo achlinan and you don't eat it, אף כל תלתא
לא ניכול. af kol tlata lo neichol. Anything with even three כשר
kosher indicators, as long as it has one non-כשר, kosher we won’t
eat. וכל שכן תרי וחד, v'chol shekein trei v'chad, certainly if it
only has two or one non-כשר kosher indicators, meaning to certainly if
it has more non-כשר kosher indicators. Okay, so now we’re saying how
do you know the rule is, we’re saying the rule is you’re
either on the list or you have four non-כשר kosher indicators. The
גמרא's Gemara saying maybe the rule should be forget the list, maybe
the rule should be one non-כשר kosher indicator is enough for a
problem. Then you’ll tell me why did you need a list? You
needed the list so I could figure out the rule. But the
rule should still be one non-כשר kosher indicator, forget if you’re don’t
worry about the list, makes it non-כשר. kosher. So the גמרא Gemara
says no. If that were true, אם כן עורב דכתב רחמנא למה
לי? im ken oreiv d'kathav Rachmana lama li? Why did it have
to mention birds on the list that had two non-כשר kosher indicators?
The עורב oreiv has two. We’re assuming twenty of them have one
non-כשר kosher indicator, the עורב oreiv has two non-כשר kosher, indicators. So
if the rule is one non-כשר kosher indicator suffices and you gave
me all the birds so I could figure it out, but why
do you bother giving me the עורב oreiv that has two non-כשר
kosher indicators? I wouldn’t need that once I figured out that one
non-כשר kosher indicator was enough. התם דאית ליה תלתא לא אכלינן, Hatam
d'ith lei tlata lo achlinan, again it I this depends whether the
word here refers to the כשר kosher or the non-כשר kosher indicator.
If it has three כשר kosher. indicators, you still can’t eat it,
which is the majority of the birds. דאית ליה תרי מבעיא? d'ith
lei trei ba'ei? Certainly the עורב oreiv that has only two כשר
kosher indicators you should not be able to to eat. Okay? So
the גמרא's Gemara saying is don’t tell me it lists all the
birds to learn out a rule that one non-כשר kosher indicator is
enough. If that were true, it would have only listed the twenty
birds with one non-כשר. kosher The fact that it also lists the
עורב oreiv that has two non-כשר, kosher then that is extra if
I would have known that one would have sufficed. So the fact
that it says עורב oreiv tells me the rule is not one
non-כשר kosher indicator. So the גמרא Gemara says... The גמרא Gemara says
okay, but at least let it be two non-כשר kosher indicators. So
לילף מעורב, leilef me-oreiv, at least learn from the example of עורב.
oreiv. So you're saying the extra example of עורב, oreiv, which normally
translates as raven, that's extra, because you could have figured that out
that it's, that it has one non-כשר kosher indicator. Fine, let it
be extra, but let's say that the Torah is using עורב oreiv
as an extra thing to teach me that there's a rule of
two non-כשר kosher indicators suffices. מה התם תרי לא אף כל תרי
לא, ma hatam trei lo af kol trei lo, in the same
way there it has two non-כשר kosher indicators, or two כשר kosher
same point, and you can't eat it, similarly anything with two or
fewer כשר kosher indicators or two or more non-כשר kosher. indicators cannot
be eaten, let that be the rule. The גמרא Gemara says no,
אם כן פרס ועזניה דכתב רחמנא למה לי? im ken peres ve-ozniyah
de-chasav Rachmana lamma li? Why would the Torah have written פרס peres
and an עזניה? ozniyah? Okay, according to the גמרא Gemara again, פרס
peres and עזניה ozniyah have three non-כשר kosher, indicators. So the again
the argument is we're saying the rule is you're either on the
list or four non-כשר kosher indicators. The גמרא's Gemara saying well why
not say the rule is one non-כשר kosher indicator? So the answer
is well then if that were true why would you need the
list? No no no, you need the list to figure out one
non-כשר kosher indicator. Okay, but if one non-כשר kosher indicator was enough,
why would you need the thing like the עורב oreiv that has
two, or the פרס peres and עזניה ozniyah have three, why did
they have to be mentioned? They should be obvious. So thinks oh
well maybe it mentioned the עורב oreiv to tell me two non-כשר
kosher indicators is really the rule. Oh but if that's true why
mention פרס peres and עזניה? ozniyah? They have three non-כשר kosher indicators.
So again they can't be that the rule is one or two
because then you wouldn't have needed the thing with more non-כשר kosher
indicators to have been mentioned. Okay. So in so in so why
don't we say השתא דאית ליה תרי לא אכלינן דאית ליה חד
מיבעיא? ahashta de-it lei trei lo achlinan de-it lei chad miba'ya? If
something has two, I keep on talking about non-כשר, kosher the גמרא
Gemara talks about the כשר kosher indicators which is the flip. But
anyways there's two כשר kosher indicators like the עורב oreiv you can't
eat it, if that were true then certainly you couldn't eat the
פרס peres and עזניה ozniyah that only have one כשר kosher indicator,
דאית ליה חד מיבעיא. de-it lei chad miba'ya. So the גמרא Gemara.
says okay, fine, you made your point. We won't go by two
because then the Torah would not have to mention פרס peres and
עזניה ozniyah that even have more non-כשר kosher indicators. But let them
be the rule. ונגמר מפרס ועזניה, ve-nigmar mi-peres ve-ozniyah, let's say the
פרס peres and עזניה ozniyah are extra, right? Because we if the
rule was two we wouldn't have needed to mention פרס peres and
עזניה, ozniyah, so mentions פרס peres and עזניה, ozniyah, that's clearly the
rule is not two. Fine, so the rule isn't two or the
Torah wouldn't have mentioned פרס peres and עזניה, ozniyah, but let the
rule be three because פרס peres and עזניה ozniyah have three non-כשר
kosher indicators. אם כן, גמרא Gemara says no, if that were true,
נשר דכתב רחמנא למה לי? nesher de-chasav Rachmana lamma li? Why would
it have to write the נשר, nesher again the vulture, right, that
has all four non-כשר kosher indicators? So basically what the argument is
like this: we have which is not a you know it's you
understand it, it's basically we have a list of twenty-four birds. Is
there a rule here of what makes a bird not כשר? kosher
So if the rule were one or two or three non-כשר kosher
indicators it would have sufficed, then it wouldn't have had to list
all the birds because at least once it would have even if
it would have required three non-כשר kosher, indicators it wouldn't have mentioned
the נשר nesher. that has four. The fact that it mentions everything
on the list proves that the only rule here would be the
נשר, nesher all four non-כשר kosher indicators makes it non-כשר kosher and
that's why now the Torah had to mention all the other birds
because all the other birds have fewer than four non-כשר kosher indicators.
Okay. So that is going back to what to explaining the ברייתא.
Because a נשר nesher, has no has all four non-כשר kosher indicators,
it that would not have had to be mentioned if anything fewer
than that would have made a bird non-כשר. kosher So from here
you see that the general rule is you need all four non-כשר
kosher indicators to make a bird non-כשר, kosher? but everything on this
list has fewer than four non-כשר kosher indicators and that's why the
Torah had to mention them to tell you the general rule is
like a נשר nesher. is non-כשר kosher but there are some birds
with fewer than four that are also non-כשר kosher and they're on
this list. Okay. So so and here's the argument, because if it
were any fewer than four we would have said like this: השתא
דאית ליה חד לא אכלינן, ahashta de-it lei chad lo achlinan, something
that has if something has even one כשר kosher indicator we wouldn't
eat it, דלית ליה כלל מיבעיא, de-leit lei klal miba'ya, how obvious
would it have been that no כשר kosher indicators we would not
have eaten it? אלא, ella, so from this we see that the
fact that the Torah had to mention נשר nesher, we could have
inferred it from some general rule shows that the only thing that
is the general rule is the נשר. Nesher אלא נשר דלית ליה
כלל הוא דלא תאכל, ella nesher de-leit lei klal hu de-lo tachal,
only the נשר Nesher
that has no כשר kosher indicators that represents the rule, something with
no כשר kosher. indicators you cannot eat, הא דאית ליה חד ha
de-it lei chad as a general rule something with even one כשר
kosher indicator אכול achol you can eat. Okay. So now we have
what we started with which is again this is not I think
how most people imagine, most people imagine that the list of twenty-four
all share a defined set of non-כשר kosher, indicators and anything with
those non-כשר kosher indicators would likewise be non-כשר. kosher The גמרא's Gemara
argument is not that way, if that were true it would not
have had to give me everything on the list, it would have
given me a small enough set from which I could have inferred
the general rule. Okay, since it gave me more than I needed
to infer the general rule The general rule is like the נשר,
nesher if it has zero kosher indicators or four non-kosher indicators depending
on which way you're describing it. That's the rule, those are non-kosher
birds. Anything with more kosher indicators or fewer non-kosher indicators is not—the
general rule is that it's kosher. But the Torah then had to
give me the list to tell me these are the exceptions. These
are things that have some of the kosher indicators and are still
going to be not kosher. And if it has all four kosher
indicators, that's certainly not on the list and that certainly is kosher.
So now as a general rule, how do I know what I
can eat in terms of the birds? I know if it has
all four kosher indicators, it's definitely not on the list and it's
kosher, end of story. So if I can use those four kosher
indicators, which by the way this is going to get to the
whole question as you might have heard about turkey, is it a
kosher bird or not? Do I really have to know the name
of the things on the list or is there a certain point
where I can sort of prove just by the characteristics that it's
kosher? So what the גמרא Gemara is assuming now is that yes,
if it has all four kosher indicators I can know it's kosher.
If it has none of the indicators, I know for certain it's
not kosher, that's what I learn out from נשר. nesher? And if
it has some mix, that's where I have to know whether it's
on the list or not on the list. That's where the Torah
says that's an exception to the rule of zero makes—only zero makes
it not kosher, because actually any positive indicators would make it kosher
except for things on the list and that's where I have to
know the name of the things on the list. And again, by
the way, the interesting irony that emerges from this is in theory
you could have a bird of prey that is kosher if it's
not on the list, and you could have a bird that is
not a bird of prey that is not kosher and that in
theory could be on the list and תוספות says those points explicitly.
Okay, so now let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes from here.
Okay, good thing that there's a lot of תוספות so it's helping
us catch up.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ואלא טעמא דכתב רחמנא נשר. Ve'ela ta'ama dechasav rachmana nesher. The
reason that we know that there's a general rule of zero kosher
indicators makes it not kosher is because the Torah gave me the
example of the נשר, nesher which again is presumably the vulture. הא
לאו הכי, Hav lav hachi, had it not given me that example,
הוה אמינא לילף מפרס ועזניה. hava amina leilaf miperes ve'ozniya. So this
is what we said before, that I could have learned from just
the other cases that the general rule and I would have said,
oh, what's the rule from פרס ועזניה? peres ve'ozniya? Three non-kosher indicators,
that means that with three non-kosher indicators you're not kosher. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, how would I have learned from those
examples? הוי ליה פרס ועזניה שני כתובים הבאים כאחד ושני כתובים הבאים
כאחד אין מלמדין. Havei lei peres ve'ozniya shenei kesuvim habaim ke'echad, veshenei
kesuvim habaim ke'echad ein melamdin. Right, when the Torah—the general
point of the Torah is is that if there's a rule, it'll
only say it once. So this is the basic hermeneutical principle of
the גמרא. Gemara It's a בנין אב, binyan av, it's a paradigm.
If it ever has to repeat a case, give you two examples,
it's basically implicitly saying it's not a rule, it's an exception. Because
if it were a rule, you wouldn't have had to give me
more than one case. The fact that you're telling it to me
again means that these are exceptions, these aren't the rule. Which is
the principle of שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. shenei kesuvim habaim ke'echad. If
the Torah ever says two examples of the—which share a rule, you
actually—your assumption is that it's an exception, it's not the rule. So
the גמרא Gemara is saying goes like this: this whole earlier discussion
basically was assuming that had the Torah given me just some other
part of the list, just the 20 initial birds, I would have
said, oh, one non-kosher indicator is enough. Or if it had given
me the פרס ועזניה peres ve'ozniya I would have said three non-kosher
indicators enough. The גמרא Gemara is saying how would you have learned
that out? I would have said that the fact that it gives
you more than one example would have forced you to say that
that isn't the rule, not that it is the rule, that it
isn't the rule. Now of course part of the answer here could
be is that given that there's a different numbers of kosher and
non-kosher indicators, right, I might not have been able to figure out
the rule without a collection of data. Right, I needed a couple
of different types of birds, right, to figure out, well, what's the
common denominator here? You know, what makes these birds special? Oh look,
they all share the following three non-kosher characteristics. I mean, to just
call them non-kosher is part of what I'm figuring out. They all
share these three characteristics, it must be that these characteristics make something
not kosher. Okay, so rather than to say, oh, well then you
wouldn't have needed more than one example, I only would have needed
more than one example if I had known from the beginning what
kosher and non-kosher characteristics are. But if I'm inferring it from the
data, I probably need more than one data point. Okay, so we'll
see the גמרא Gemara will answer something along these lines, but that's
the question. All of this assumed that I could have learned out
from, you know, some of the birds the general rules of one
or two or three non-kosher characteristics. How would I have learned it
out? Once it's more than one example, it should have labeled it
as an exception. So the גמרא Gemara's says: גמירי Gemiri no, we
have a tradition. דאיכא בהאי ליכא בהאי דאיכא בהאי ליכא בהאי. De'ika
behai leika behai, de'ika behai leika behai. So this is pretty much
what I said to you, which is that they don't all share
the— same non-kosher characteristics. Some animals, yes, a lot, we said that
all the animals have at least one, and some have two, and
the פרס Peres and the עזניה Azniyah have three. But when it
comes to פרס Peres and עזניה Azniyah having three, one of them
could have A, B, and C, and the other could have, you
know, A, C, and D or something like that. So if it
had just given me one of those examples, I wouldn't have said
any three non-kosher characteristics, I would have said specifically A, B, and
C, or specifically A, C, and D.
So the גמרא Gemara would have had to... so the תורה Torah
would have had to have given me both so I could say,
ah, but at least what they share is some three three out
of four non-kosher characteristics. I needed two to be able to say
three out of four and not just a specific A, B, and
C or specifically like A, C, and D or something of that
nature. So that's why I would have learned from that the rule
of three and then except that the תורה Torah went to say
נשר nesher to which I learned the rule of four. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says מכדי, Michdi, one minute, let's take a look.
עשרים וארבע עופות טמאים הוו. Esrim v'arba ofot tme'im havu. There are
twenty-four non-kosher birds. אי אפשר דחד איכא בהני וליכא בהני. Iy efshar
d'chad ika behani v'leka behani. So nevertheless, there are twenty-four non-kosher birds.
If you look at all of them, it is impossible, right, that
there are not two birds on that list that share the same
non-kosher characteristics, okay? And this is easier if you focus on the
twenty. We said the twenty have three kosher סימנים, simanim all of
them. Out of twenty out of the twenty-four. Or let's say it
in an easier way, only one non-kosher characteristic. So fine, but just
reasonably speaking now, logically it is possible, and we're going to say
that in a minute, but, but, you know, from a reasonable perspective,
what is the likelihood that of twenty birds, each of them having
one out of four kosher סימנים, simanim that you're not going to
have... so some have just A, you know, non-kosher characteristic. Some have
just B, some have just C, some have just D. Presumably at
least there's always going to be one of those things, presumably in
every single one of those there'll be at least two birds, right?
If you have twenty-four and some have problem A and some have
problem B and some have problem C and some have problem D,
presumably there's going to be at least one of in any one
of those problems at least two birds will have the same non-kosher
characteristic. And if that's true, why did the תורה Torah have to
mention both of them? Right? Because again the principle: if that were
the rule, it wouldn't have repeated it. So from the fact that
the תורה Torah is mentioning two birds that have D, and two
birds that have C, and two birds that have A, and two
birds that have B, from that you can figure out that none
of them are the rule. Because if any one of those, either
A alone or B alone or C alone or D alone were
the rule, the תורה Torah would not have given me more than
one example. And the fact that the תורה Torah is giving me
more than one example proves that it's the exception and not the
rule. Okay, everybody still following me more or less? Okay. So again
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, it started by saying that
I would have looked at this evidence and I would have determined
as a rule what, you know, one non-kosher characteristic is enough, two
is not enough, three is enough, and finally I said, no, no,
no, I'm only going to look at the נשר nesher, and I'm
going to say four non-kosher characteristics makes it non-kosher. Now the גמרא
Gemara is questioning the הווא אמינא, my havamina, what I would have
thought. I would have thought to have looked at this evidence and
inferred by the twenty twenty out of the twenty-four that one non-kosher
is enough. גמרא Gemara's says: how could you have inferred that? You
would have always had at least two examples of the same problem,
and that should have labeled it as an exception, not the rule.
So how could you have thought to have looked at this evidence
and called it the rule? Yes.
You could have exhausted the combinations with just eight birds.
Right, that's essentially what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Yeah. So the
fact that you could have given all of these examples without, right,
without without, you know, without twenty-four birds, how can you say I
would have looked at this evidence and come up with the rule?
How could you have thought there was a rule here since there's
going to definitely be amongst these twenty-four two always two examples of
any one of the rules? Okay, that's the גמרא's question. And if
there's more than one example, it labels it as not a rule.
So the גמרא says like this, so the גמרא says, you know
what, although it's not it is possible to have something that is
not two examples of the same rule. גמירי, Gmiri, we have a
tradition, עשרים וארבע עופות טמאים הוו, esrim v'arba ofot tme'im havu, of
the twenty-four non-kosher birds, וארבע סימנים, v'arba simanim, and there are four
non-kosher סימנים, simanim, or excuse me, four kosher סימנים. simanim, I keep
on talking about non-kosher, I think it's easier to think about, but
the גמרא keeps on talking about the kosher סימנים, simanim, so I'm
sorry about that confusion. There are four kosher סימנים. simanim. תלתא הדרי
בכולהו עשרין. Tlata hadari b'kulu esrin. There are twenty there are three
of the kosher סימנים simanim, repeat among twenty of the birds. Okay,
בכולהו עשרין מהם. b'kulu esrin mehem. שלשה שלשה. shlosha shlosha. Excuse me,
three repeat among all of them. עשרים מהם שלשה שלשה, Esrim mehem
shlosha shlosha, twenty of them have three of the non-kosher סימנים, simanim.
ותרי בעורב, v'trei b'orev, two in the עורב, orev, חד בפרס וחד
בעזניה. chad b'peres v'chad b'ozniyah.
One of and one of those kosher סימנים simanim in the פרס
Peres and one in the עזניה. Azniyah. דאיכא בהאי ליכא בהאי, de'ika
behai leka behai, and what exists in one... doesn't exist in the
other ones. What does this mean? It means that if you imagine
A, B, and C are the kosher סימנים. simanim, So of the,
of the 24 non-kosher birds, the 20 at the base level have
A, B, and C kosher סימנים, simanim they don't have the D.
At the next level, the עורב orev has two of the kosher,
two of the non-kosher, that let's say A and B. At the
third level, the פרס peres and the עזניה, azniyah, so the פרס
peres has A. Okay, now what is the only so far kosher
סימן siman that hasn't been mentioned? D. Right? So of 22 out
of the 24, and נשר Nesher is at the top, it has
none of the kosher סימנים, simanim. 22 of the 24 at the
bottom of the pyramid have A, B, and C, you know, at
the next level have just A and B, and at the next
level have just A. That's the פרס. peres. The עזניה azniyah is
an outlier here, and the עזניה azniyah is the only one of
those that has kosher סימן siman D. Okay, so now what it
is telling me is of the פרס peres and the עזניה azniyah
so, so, I would have said your whole question is how could
I have learned a general rule, there's always a something that is
a repeated example and if it's a repeated example it says, it
says no, because the עזניה azniyah has kosher סימן siman D and
all the other birds, the ones that have some kosher סימנים, simanim,
have from the collection of A, B, and C, but none of
them have from D. Only the עזניה azniyah has D. So I
would have said, let's learn from the עזניה azniyah which is a
singular example, it's not a repeated example, it's a single example, that
it had kosher סימן siman D, that anything, you know, that anything
with just kosher סימן siman D is going to be, is going
to be, you know, anything that lacks both A, B, and C,
all three of those, is not kosher and that that's the rule.
All right, so that's the Gemara's point. I'm if you're getting a
little lost, I apologize, I hope it's not my explanation, it's a
complicated Gemara. But the basic point here again is what? Is why
would I have said oh let's learn the rule from these birds,
aren't all examples repeating? And since all examples are whatever the rule
would have been would have been repeated, I couldn't have learned from
it because you can't learn from a repeated example, שני כתובים הבאים
כאחד. shenei kesuvim haba'im ke'echad. And then it says no, it's not
true all the examples are repeated. It is true that there's always
going to be more than one case of these birds that have
kosher סימן siman A, more than one case that has kosher סימן
siman B, more than one case that has kosher סימן siman C,
but there's kosher סימן siman D that the עזניה azniyah has or
the פרס peres has that no other animal has. Or to say
it the way I would say it, there are no other animal
has A, B, and C, all three, three specific non-kosher סימנים. simanim,
Meaning, you know, let me reframe it in terms of non-kosher סימנים.
simanim, In my mind it makes it easier because you're thinking about
labeling it as non-kosher, you want to be thinking about the non-kosher
סימנים. simanim. So everything at the bottom let us has non-kosher סימן
siman D, let's say it that way. At the next level it
has non-kosher סימן siman D and C. At the next level it
has non-kosher סימן siman D, C, and B. Okay, so do you
have repeated examples of certain non-kosher סימנים? simanim. Yes. But there's one
case of non-kosher סימן siman A, right, that you have no example
of except for the פרס peres or the עזניה. azniyah. That is
the only animal that has non-kosher סימן, siman, you know, A. And
therefore I would have said that that would have sufficed to label
a bird not kosher. Okay, so I could so your question is
how could you have learned out a rule, isn't everything repeating? No,
there's one not kosher סימן siman that doesn't repeat. And that's what
I would have learned out to would have been the rule.
Okay, so the Gemara says,
so the נשר? Nesher.
No, the נשר Nesher is different than the עזניה. azniyah. Okay, then
what's...
it's okay, no, the again, using it by talking about non-kosher סימנים,
simanim. okay, the,
the, I just want to hear this again. The birds at the
bottom all have one, one non-kosher סימן, siman, either A, B, or
C. One of those three they have, but they don't have the
D non-kosher סימן. siman. The next set of birds, the עורב, orev,
has two of the non-kosher סימנים, simanim? what let's say A and
B. At the next set of birds has three of the non-kosher
סימנים, simanim, A, B, and C. The נשר Nesher has all four
of the non-kosher סימנים, simanim, A, B, C, and D. But that's
going to be the rule. The rule is going to be the
נשר, Nesher, if it has A, B, C, and D, it's not
kosher. Okay, but Gemara saying how would I have thought to learn
a rule about any two, one, or two or three non-kosher סימנים,
simanim, don't I have repeating examples? Says no, you don't have repeating
examples because you notice I haven't mentioned D. Except for the פרס,
peres, that will have let's say A, B, and D. And that
would have been the only example that had A, B, and D.
And therefore I would say that maybe any bird with A, B,
and D is going to be not kosher. Ah, don't we have
more than one example? No, it just so happens we only have
one example of A, B, and D. So only that would have
been not kosher, and that would have been the rule, that would
have been suffice to learn a rule from because it would have
been the only example. So let's just finish this up.
מהו דתימא לילף מיניה, mahu deteima leilaf mineh, let's learn from the
one that has A, B, and D, the only one that has
the D problem, so כתב רחמנא נשר. kasav Rachmana nesher. נשר דלית
ליה מכלל הוא דלא תיכול, Nesher delais lei mikhlal hu delo teichol,
only a נשר that has no non-כשר kosher סימנים, simanim, meaning then
A, B, C, and D, that's the one you can't eat from.
האי Ha'ee to try to say נשר. נשר דלית ליה מכלל הוא
דלא תיכול, Nesher delais lei mikhlal hu delo teichol, only a נשר
that has no non-כשר kosher סימנים, simanim, meaning then A, B, C,
and D, that's the one you can't eat from. האי דאית בה
חד, Ha'ee de'is bei chad, okay, so if one has just one
כשר kosher סימן in theory you can eat it. So that was
a little complicated again for us that we're not bothered by having
multiple data points to infer a rule, it's not an issue. But
the simple, the bottom line is, I realize that was a little
tough going, but the bottom line is actually quite simple. The basic
assumption is like this, that it's not true that all the birds
share a well-defined set of non-כשר kosher סימנים, and the גמרא
actually, it says, actually it says that if it were true we
wouldn't be able to understand why the תורה Torah had to give
us the full list. The only way of understanding why the תורה
had to give us the full list is because the list is
really exceptions. This is the גמרא's way about, about coming about it.
So the rule has to be only an animal with all four
non-כשר kosher סימנים like the נשר is the rule is non-כשר. kosher
Anything with fewer, in principle, is כשר, kosher unless you're on the
list. If you're on the list you have some כשר, kosher some
non-כשר, kosher. but anything that but so basically again, if you have
all four כשר kosher. סימנים you are definitely not on the list
and you're כשר, kosher, you don't need to know what's on the
list, in principle. If you have four non-כשר kosher, סימנים, that's the
rule we learned from the נשר, you're definitely not כשר. kosher, And
if you have some mix, then maybe כשר, kosher, maybe not כשר,
kosher. that's why the תורה needed the list. And according to the
גמרא again, the reason the תורה needed the, the only way to
explain why the תורה needed to give you a list and couldn't
have just given you a rule was because there is no rule
when it comes to the list. When it comes to a mix
of כשר, kosher, non-כשר kosher, birds, of, of, excuse me, fewer than
four non-כשר kosher, סימנים, some are כשר, kosher some are not, and
that's why you had to give a list. But the only rule
of non-כשר kosher, is four non-כשר kosher סימנים, and the only rule
of כשר kosher is four כשר סימנים, and anything in between, you
have to know what's on the list. Okay.